[Music]
john
john has this world uh called reinventio
um which is this idea of of reinventing
and discovering
um you know perennial things
uh um and uh
and then i wrote this article recent or
a while ago called
we need a renaissance not not a
revolution so i wonder if you guys could
perhaps riff on on this idea of well
what do you think of my idea that that
renaissance is more appropriate to the
time than
than revolution and that's what we need
to be doing
uh for the future and then maybe we can
we can talk a bit more about
um the religion that is not a religion
um
or john's idea and and maybe your idea
of concrete utopia and maybe
maybe we can go deeper into the ideas of
education and that sort of thing
that sounds good i mean the term is
actually from kerry his book on
augustine um
and he says he wants to he wanted to use
uh
it comes out in english and he's unhappy
with the english translations it's
augustine's invention of the inner self
and he said the word he wanted was latin
but the publishers wouldn't let him use
it
the word is inventio which means both it
means both to invent and to discover
yeah and uh i i i'm very
interested in that as a replacement term
for the term that i was always unhappy
with
the idea of sort of salvaging from the
past
can i connect one more thing before you
continue the reason i thought this
concept was important is because i asked
myself the question
what do we need to reinvent the oh it's
hard to say that yeah i like that i like
um
oh and and it occurs to me everything we
need to reinvent practically
everything i mean in terms of
institutions but at the same time we
don't want to give you know we want to
salvage
to use your word again yeah what matters
or
or what what you know the the perennial
and zach talks about neoperennialism
so i i mean i like i i like in fact what
you're doing with that idea andrew how
are you
taking it up as let's go through various
some central
normative constructs and uh see if
you know if the inventio is is uh
required and then what that looks like
i'm very interested in that project
we've been doing it you and chris and i
and
i'd like to continue that um and
i'm also interested in um
the thing you propose i i've been
contrasting the actual revolution with
the french revolution and some of the
things i've been
talking about um and then what we need
is something more like the axial
revolution
than the french revolution and that
sounds like it could at least be put
into constructive dialogue
with your idea of renaissance versus
revolution yeah
and the other sorry to keep jumping in
here but the other
the other uh thing that i thought that
we could
reinvent eo i have a really hard time
saying that reinventio
um is because it's it's such a concern
of zacks
is how we think about you know social
justice and that kind of thing i thought
that might be a
interesting i'd like to talk about way
to go
who can bring care and concern to it uh
because um it seems to me right now that
the discourse around social justice
is becoming uh very oversimplified
and it's either being what's currently
happening uh i think
and the fact that some people even take
this as an insult is kind of telling
i think what's happening right now with
the social justice movement is
we're actually seeing it's a religion
much more than it's just a political
movement uh because it's it's it's
serving a lot of functions that religion
serves and i'd like to talk about
um what like with zach i guess
about what that might be like what does
it mean in terms of the broader idea
that we've been already
talking about about well the reinvention
of education and the
the deeper connections between education
and enculturation
and between education and virtue and
we've talked to also
you know the connections between
education and
the mythopoetic discourse both between
people and within people
i think the pursuit of justice without
the pursuit of software son
is a brave mistake and so
it seems to me that one of the places
that was supposed to mediate and
moderate between those two
is education and so there's a lot i'd
like to talk can you remind me what
sauferson is what that term means
jefferson is the untranslatable one of
the four
cardinal greek virtues and and like
wisdom you can make a good case that
sauferson is actually more of a meta
virtue than a virtue
but it's it's it's often paired with
justice uh plato
famously does it in the republic where
he talks about justice in the city
and it's reflected in terms of this
state within the psyche
a kind of inner justice and software
it's kind of
it's it's kind of a culture of the
psyche so that
it is reliably self-organizing to pursue
what is good and what is true and what
is beautiful
totally and that's why the the paidia or
the basic educational structure
of the polity is so primary
uh because you could yeah yeah yeah you
could set up
uh on the books just system
uh let's say you know basic income and
universal healthcare and all my social
miracles let's say
but you end up not fixing the problem
with digital media ecology
and not fixing the problem with
education and you get this kind of
uh total fragmentation of awareness
and removal from the grounding of of
uh like i won't even be able to say the
word of wisdom basically within the
individual person
and that's where it's all off and that's
where the
issue with the discussion of justice and
education comes together which is the
theme of my
first book but you know a lot of what
we're seeing with the
kind of uprising and the so-called
social justice warriors
you know most of this has to do with
this context of socialization
and especially the informational
technologies in which individuals are
socialize and regulate self-esteem more
than has to do with concepts of justice
like if we could get into rawlsy
injustice and
platinus's notions of justice and then
you can look at justice
even in buddhism and other discourses
that don't use that term but there are
ways of thinking about it
those are very different from the in
kind of personality complexes uh
and character structures that are being
formed in these
socialization environments of uh
informational
like digital informational ecologies and
um
yeah well i was gonna say like it like
part of what i mean by it being a
religious phenomenon
is one of the things religions do is
they tend to generate
um normative claims they generate they
tend to generate new virtues often
right like you know christianity makes
love and faith into virtues and they
weren't before
we now take it for granted you know
thomas aquinas has to write a large
piece on it
trying to explain why love is a virtue
etc
and so i think we're
like we're very we're i think we're
close and it's in a way that's
concerning to me
to to outrage becoming a virtue
and this ties into what you're saying
zach because
we know i mean sorry i don't mean to i'm
not generally not conspiratorial at all
but we know the algorithms on social
media polarize people
and drive them to outrage and to extreme
statements and to flip
reasoning because that promotes
right connection and advertising and
viewing et cetera et cetera
and people i think is what you're
alluding to with social media people are
being
you know they're being educated in a
very profound way
into a
way of being in which outrage seems like
a virtuous thing
and i'm not clear that outrage is
should ever be considered a candidate
virtue
this is completely independent about
what the issue the outrage is directed
at yeah
i think there's relevant issues
important issues i'm not denying that at
all
that's not what i'm talking about i want
to make that really clear i'm talking
about
the promotion within sort of a religious
framework
of outrage as a virtue like the people
will often say to me in conversations
and they'll say it sort of critically
aren't you outraged about this
and i'll say well i have arguments
against it and i think you know
but they're they're upset with me
because i'm not
outraged and that's that's the phenomena
i'm putting my finger on right now
i i just have a thought here just just
give another another perspective
because i was listening to the jewish
rabbi and he was talking and saying all
these people are they're out in the
street looting and stuff
destroying things you know uh because of
their their outrage
um why wouldn't they do that if they
don't have a proper
uh basic religious education that's what
the rabbi was saying
you know why wouldn't they do that if
they didn't have any idea
of of uh any refined idea of of
of what is you know what is virtue
so that's just i agree with what you're
saying i just i just
that other that that this is tying into
zack's idea that you know that we we
need we need uh
to to bring sort of um
not religio back into education or um
both of you guys idea i think right i
mean and it's
i would say something more like the you
know social media
is hijacking the power
of religion essentially that they you
know religion is the ultimate
psyop right it's the ultimate limbic
system
neocortical integration like capture
people yeah and it's always promoted
violence to some extent
like so there needs to be and i think
what
what you know facebook and other outlets
have done is basically
found a way to get you know as far as i
can tell like
um almost randomly generated religious
fervor and scapegoating dynamics in
particular
it's random right that's that's the
thing it's yeah well it's
it's not entirely random not entirely
again i'm with john
like i can talk just social justice all
day like i'm actually
very uh sincerely concerned
about society not because it's about to
self-terminate
in terms of existential and ecological
collapse but in because of the
injustices that have been perpetrated
especially in the past
20 or 15 years so there's a long
conversation to have there so it's
it's a distraction from actual social
justice distraction
it's like it's like a smoke screen i
think it's a smoke screen being run in
between us
it's like a simulacrum of social justice
or something or simulacrum of religion
or or
yeah well then it was like michael white
who was one of the
organizers of the occupy movement wrote
a book at the end of protest i'd talk
about a lot because it's brilliant
and he was like listen at a certain
point the thing
occupied became it started to function
for its own representation in the social
media
field right which is to say like you
weren't doing it to do it you were doing
it to represent it into the social media
field
as a as a signal you know and uh
and so that's part of the dynamic here
is that there's yeah the simulations
layered on top of the actual reality and
often makes the actual reality
less less real less important so people
are like
abandoning sanity for the sake of
signaling allegiance to you know
meta-narratives propagated through the
social media film
which which sort of is a gerardian
phenomenon right it's like it's like
these
these mob develop and they look for a
scapegoat
you know and the scapegoat is sort of
random and uh
you know and they prop the scapegoat up
and
you know sacrifice him and then make him
into a god of some
some kind yeah and so i mean the general
takeaway is like
you know the first move has to be
something about that like the first move
actually has to be
reclaiming the basic foundations that
allow us to communicate
right um which is to say kind of rolling
back
the column the colonization of the life
world to roll back the colonization of
the life world and create
actual sane and fair containers for
socialization and intergenerational
transmission
because the social justice thing social
justice warriors quote unquote
it's also generational understand that
you know
you're looking at young people um you're
looking at young people who are
uh being used strategically
and yeah so it's it's a disconcerting
situation
and uh i agree there's a sense of
religiosity and religious kind of fervor
to it
which i attribute to the kind of
exquisite
uh advertising and algorithmical
capacity of the social media platforms
uh because they've they're they know the
right as advertisers do they know
exactly the right
set of words right the simple abstract
mappings a couple abstract contents next
to one another
with a certain word sound power that
just
is on a poster and it just who started
that good question
like where do these things begin and how
do they propagate through the social
media field
and become attachable to the self
brought up into the self's
self-esteem regulation
self-understanding uh
and now you're running a kind of modus
operandi for your life where
your representation of yourself in
social media is the actual basis of your
self-esteem
and your immediate and your immediate
your immediate lived environment
is not the basis where you're getting
your self-esteem um
and uh that's the total capture of the
cell system
by the kind of attention harvesting
information capitalism or surveillance
capitalism
that's the most egregious because it's
not just that over stimulation
and capture of like through hyperstimuli
the limbic system
it's also capture of the self-esteem
regulation mechanism and identity
formation mechanism
uh through that kind of signaling
and and like uh you know pseudo diet
pseudo uh that's the right word pseudo
attachment or
pseudo recognition system that the
social media kind of puts up as a mirror
um so anyway it kind of kept going there
but
i think that i wanted to get that he was
stuff out it was good
i mean that's that's the i mean
the part you ended on it circles back to
the concern i have
right that when you when you sever the
virtues from each other
you tend to get what one of the things
you get is you get the confusion
of having a self-representation with
actually being in the process of
self-knowledge
and but
we have to remember that you know people
getting trained in these
patterns of behavior and and that are
ultimately manipulated outside of their
self-knowledge
they can be directed other ways right
this machine the fact that it might be
directed towards causes that you and i
believe in right now
doesn't mean that this machine can't be
equally directed towards causes
that we we think are like wrong
and that's my concern
and i have no faith in corporate
capitalism to keep my best interests at
heart
i have no faith in that whatsoever and
so that that's what i mean
i'm concerned about uh the the fact that
the the powers that be are just sort of
you know just there's the uncritical
sort of this is just a wonderful thing
that's happening and it's like
uh i don't know i i i'm very concerned
about what we're what we're teaching
people
uh about how to try and bring about
change uh because
i always worry about especially when i
see
the corporate capitalists people just
jumping on board this and loving it and
saying it's good and
like that that also makes me like why
are you doing this
you're not you're not better you're not
doing this for any moral argument you're
doing yeah
you're benefiting from this in some way
and
and so again i don't i generally have a
heuristic of not
going anywhere towards conspiracy
theories but i think the idea that
this has layers of causation below it
that that the demonstrators are not
aware of
and that those layers can be put to uh
other ends that could turn out to be
what i would regard as seriously immoral
um that's that's a very deep concern i
have it's a bit what daniel
schmacktenberg always talks about is
truth is
something true becomes weaponized right
it's something something is something
that is maybe a beautiful expression
becomes a corporate logo or
you know it's that and it's my overall
concern right
that the thing that one of the most
powerful biases that keeps us from being
rational
is to find the products of our cognition
super salient
and not be concerned with attend to or
value the processes
by which we try to achieve our goals i
mean that's
that's that's both that's an argument
that comes out of sort of deep
philosophical tradition
and you know overwhelming i think
empirical recent empirical work and
experimental work and
that so i have a concern that
that as i said we're not
paying attention to how are we like
what is going on such that we're doing
these things that we're doing
like it's a very socratic concern
and it's a difficult thing to bring up
because i do think
it's clear there's police brutality it's
it's clear that police have to be
demilitarized
i mean and zach and i've been talking
about this before and i've been talking
about it for a long time
he's of course talked about it more
eloquently our culture as a whole should
be
shifting its resources into education in
ways
we haven't been doing i i think these
are important in things that have to be
pursued
and the problem i have is i try to talk
to people about
it's an important part of problem
solving is to make sure you have
formulated the problem well
and i'm not sure the problem has been
formulated well and i'm even afraid to
bring that criticism up
i could you know i yeah look i i think
your goals are right but the way you're
formulating trying to achieve those
goals
is exactly thwarting you from achieving
them and so that's the concern
but these people actually become beyond
criticism because
because they are they they are in a
state of of religious
uh fanaticism you know so you you can't
you can't
go into a a in-depth analysis because
it's it's an article of faith isn't it
when people talk about these things well
i mean i don't i don't know about all
the people that are involved i don't
know how to
i don't know there's no data and i don't
want to pronounce on all of them i'm
only talking about
sort of what i think what zach and i are
talking about the way
in which what's
sort of the uh what do i want to say i
want to see the media presence
what like the the complicit thing that's
going on between the media and some of
the demonstrators and some of the
speakers on behalf of the movement
that's what i'm talking about i i
imagine there's large
numbers of people there that are there
you know what a genuine motive that are
trying
and trying to i don't want to i wasn't
really pronouncing
on the demonstrators or or the issues i
was more pronouncing
on a certain kind of uh fanaticism that
doesn't
doesn't allow for for um
any kind uh you know mistake or you know
of speech
or um uh you know or or wrong
view or you know so we can't have a
conversation when when it's it's just
it's it's so that's yeah totally you
can't have a conversation
and that but that's true across the
board
it's not just yeah yeah it's not true
for those people or protesting
it's true for the the whole whole
spectrum of people
right and so that's again i think back
to
the kind of social media digital kind of
informational landscape
you know it's it's running interference
on our ability to be together
and to stay in the space of reasons as
opposed to retreat to strategic
relationship to one another
uh and so yeah words are
kind of the first possible weapons and
justice is of course one of those
beautiful words which is now
like sometimes used pejoratively like
the social justice words pejorative
you know like and justice itself
as i said is a philosophical concept
huge moment of truth there massive
important world historical moment of
truth in the elaboration and
sophistication of reasoning about the
nature of justice this is just the case
and
moral development psja kohlberg when you
look at
the nature of socialization and
perspective taking capacity and the
insights into the into kind of the deep
structure of the social world
uh ideas of fairness and uh things of
that nature
all true right and as you're saying
schmucktenberger hit it on the head that
it's exactly because it's true there's a
moment of truth nestled in there
that you can layer all of this other
stuff on uh
which ends up turning that truth into
something that's
weaponizable in the sense of that you
can create scapegoating
dynamics around it and multi-polar traps
and social media fields
which is counterproductive again i've
been thinking about this word
counterproductive
it also relates to the iotogenic plague
or you know counterproductive medicine
counterproductive social justice
counterproductive school
counterproductive so many things um
have become counterproductive in in our
institutions and
and um yeah and then and again micah
white and it's
demonstrated back with the uh
the big you know world trade
organization
protests like quebec and the battle in
seattle and those things like the
medium of protest itself has largely
been
captured through intelligence upgrades
within
police and military operations and other
sectors
and so and none of the advertising so
it's it's a kind of advertisement right
isn't it well it's not just that it's a
kind of advertising it's that
there's we just know for example that
one of the ways occupy wall street was
taken down was just by putting
undercover cops in there who disrupted
consensus-based processing right
so group hippie's trying to get together
save the world they're going to run the
whole thing on consensus-based
processing and you put one undercover
cap in there and he just
doesn't agree to anything and nothing
moves right you can't decide where to
march
because this guy so that's a benign
example of other activities that we know
have basically captured
and then money being routed in from all
sides
to keep certain movements alive and to
specifically empower
certain organizers as opposed to other
organizers and
this is well documented as a part of
what protest culture has become
i don't want to talk too political here
but i i remember
something about in russia that that
putin was he was funding
both sides besides it was against him
and
and the side that was for him and he was
funding them both because he knew that
by getting people all worked up they
would just become distracted and
and uh that way he could keep keep power
right
you know and uh
large foreign governments wouldn't
structure that's keeping
existing test movements and civil
disrupts going the united states is not
like we know china for example does
amazing
unconventional warfare
so so it's just this question of looking
past the surface
running the hermeneutics of suspicion
which is part of the social justice
thing is running a hermeneutic suspicion
run the hermeneutics of suspicion
on your own shit and start looking more
deeply
into the the many layers of what's
actually unfolding
as opposed to what might be unfolding
and again i i'm arguing not that the
injustice doesn't exist i'm arguing that
the media spectacle is actually running
a screen between
us and the actual injustices and the
actual ways to get in
start to do things about them and it
begins with having civil
conversations and engaging in collective
inquiry about our shared reality
which means finding the space of reason
again
and you know moving back from that
retreat into
pure strategic action and the worst
place we're seeing the strategic action
is in the intergenerational transmission
right and this i've spoken about this
before but like uh
the difference between raising children
and designing children
and what advertising does is design
children facebook is designing children
it's not raising them yeah so
raising a child is a non-strategic
relationship
of communicative action mutual
understanding uh
designing a child is a strategic
intervention
you require words in the sense of even
trying to establish mutual understanding
and so that's part of what we're seeing
here is actually
for a certain threshold of generational
transmission there was this
much higher incidence of purely
strategic interaction
as the main event during
childhood development and socialization
right and that's
that's terrible you know that that that
kind of disables the capacity
for uh non-strategic interaction
and would actually make one deeply
suspicious of anyone who wasn't acting
strategically because you'd think it was
just some higher level strategy
and so that's so interesting
now i think i've lost you're you're
cutting out a bit
zach um are you experiencing zach
cutting out a bit or is that just me uh
john oh uh he's also cutting up for me
you're cutting out just a little bit so
that's mine
maybe you could just repeat the last
thing you've said because i it was very
interesting and
uh i was i was basically saying that i
believe in this is a hypothesis
but give me some years and we'll see
what's happening but
i believe that there's been a situation
such that
at a certain point in time maybe 2016
maybe 2010.
the predominant communicational context
in which socialization was occurring in
the united states became
more strategic than not which is to say
that the main experience i'm having of
other people is that they're relating to
me strategically
including my own family teachers and
especially the screen that i'm looking
at all day
and it becomes so normal that you don't
realize that there's a space of
non-strategic
communication right we're the unforced
force of the better argument
where mutual agreement and mutual
understanding are primary and content is
sometimes secondary and a whole bunch of
other factors which make for
healthy socialization environment where
you can regulate self-esteem you know in
a
in a way that's mediated through the
embodied experiences of people around
you and things of that nature
and so yeah the idea that when
social media started to tip towards one
of the main effects
of socialization and identity formation
you also got it tipping towards the main
environment of identity formation being
one that's
strategic an environment of design as
opposed to an environment which one's
being raised
so that means beyond a certain threshold
generational threshold there's a
massive kind of like opening in the
character structure
the force for something like infection
or manipulation
by social complex social media fields
and it's a strange hypothesis but it's
one of the only ways that i can explain
what's happening
and the more you look at the nature of
social media and realize what an
engineered
environment it is like just how
uh just how complex the psychometric
micro targeting becomes and just
how easily it captures you just how
dedicated they were to figuring out how
to capture
you yeah not like people like you you
uh you realize it's it's a deeply uh
you know deeply kind of it's is not the
right word it's a profoundly
unprecedented
context of socialization for humans
because it's
it's um usually not the case like
usually the
most of the modality you're having in
communication is non-strategic
right it's trust-based and relational
and embodied with family members or
members of your community now in rare
situations like warfare
or serious abuse or maybe you're like a
really bad
orphanage i mean there's definitely
scenarios where it would be different
you feel like everyone's strategically
relating to you
and manipulating you uh but to have
you know so i'm just it's it's one of
the things that takes me back
and makes me worry when i see the
kind of degradation of discourse and the
weaponization
of language and the kind of like use of
almost
advertising grade communicative tricks
by young people in social media fields
to get a point to get across like
complex
ideas that they haven't actually thought
through that they're signaling
allegiance to a meta-narrative to
you know signal group membership uh but
they're running very sophisticated
[Music]
like media tropes which they're just
second nature to them because of the
context of their
socialization where you're not reasoning
you're advertising
constantly like you know you're not
relating
your strategizing so what's the way out
of the matrix
like uh you know i brought up this idea
of a renaissance and you talked about
stepping back
um we have to step back on some level
right we have to
we have to rediscover um our
neighborhood and
like repurpose you know all this garbage
we create and
um there's some things that i think i
mean part of
part a piece i would first of all add to
what zach was saying
the reason why i was silent is because i
was in complete agreement with it
very eloquently expressed i think
there's added dimensions
i mean so slogans work on the knowledge
illusion i think it's
like i think it's put on amphetamines by
social media
so the knowledge illusion is people
regularly confuse access to knowledge
with possession of knowledge
they deeply confuse it they think they
know
when they don't and you can and it's
actually kind of a shocking thing to do
with people
like you ask people you know how a
bicycle works and they're oh yeah of
course i do very confidently
and then you say okay we'll draw a
picture of a bicycle and show kids that
will explain to me how it works
and they start doing it and they realize
they have no idea how a bicycle works
or a toilet and what's interesting
is when you translate this over into
social interaction
when you ask people to state their
values on an issue they polarize
but when you ask them to explain the
mechanisms of the issue that is at work
they actually move towards agreeing with
each other and understanding each other
so right if i ask you know what's the
republican take on this at the
democratic way
people will go on this but if you ask me
if you actually ask people
but what are the causes of poverty i
don't you know
not what do you think we should do about
it but what are the causes of it what
are the processes
and then what happens is people realize
that their ignorance is much more shared
than that and they move towards right
actually coming to have an empathetic
understanding of other people
but the problem with social media is it
it takes the knowledge illusion and
explodes it because people
are being educated right to believe
that their access to the internet is the
same thing as having knowledge
and and that seems so innocent because
we're thinking oh but it's like it's
just like an electronic library
but no it's not it's not right it's
overwhelmingly not it really puts
because in a library you have to go and
search
you have to gather things together you
have to put a lot of thought in you have
to talk to other people
the internet it's got everything
organized for you it's got algorithms
you're invaded by algorithms right right
and so
you see what i'm saying it magnifies the
knowledge
illusion and and this is again what and
if you take that
and you put that with what zach saying
about how
people are basically i would call it a
kind of modal confusion that they're
into
uh manipulating each other rather than
uh the deep recognition that we become
persons through each other a kind of a
gaping notion
that has been lost uh when you put those
two together when people think they know
uh when they don't and they think they
don't
need people when they do uh i i mean
then you're in
you're into a very very dangerous
situation because people will then
make they will have it's like it's it's
like the line from yates right
uh about you know the the the
passionate intensity uh for for things
that
um are actually very very questionable
and so i guess what i'm trying to get at
is
i think that well
i propose that we need to
get back to a way of thinking
about discourse
that integrates self-knowledge
the creation of personhood and the
exploration
of uh of deep understanding
back together and that's what i'm trying
to do with the whole dialectic deal
logos project
that's why i think this project is
central because teaching
people that speech
can be a place in which human
being personhood that
and also selfhood right i mean this is
the socratic idea
that that you're knowing yourself
if you if you think if you're prejudiced
to believe because i think it's the kind
of prejudice
that we've been culturated that
self-knowledge
is basically an act that's achieved
through introspection
or as as access through
self-representation
whereas the socratic thing is no no
self-knowledge is revealed only in
discourse
with others because that it's only there
where it becomes clear what you are
committed to and what you actually know
and so i'm trying to argue for that's
what i that's why
i this project i've been pursuing so
deeply and
this is why i think i want to put it
into dialogue with what zach's proposing
about education
i think of the attempt to
reverse engineer reinventio via logos
is central to everything we're talking
about here because we have
taken all of these functions and we've
pulled them apart
and then we've made ourselves pray to
manipulation
and to knowledge illusion and to
commodore confusion
and to confusing self-representation
with self-knowledge
and self-transformation and so i think
that with reintegrating speech
communitas transformation
aspiration i that's why i i
i think this is central and i think this
is a project very different
from the projects that are usually
labeled political in our current
discourse
yeah i mean i'm good i'm sorry how do we
how can we even be
political i have a hard time being
political myself and zac i guess this
you said you were radicalized because of
circumstances and you
so you totally but i went i went not
into it because because
but i you know i almost feel like i'm
i'm i almost feel like an irresponsible
person because
i i i don't know where to put my foot in
in the political world
um i haven't i speak about
i speak about metapolitics and what
john's describing
uh with the die logos project is
absolutely not a political movement
it is political and it may be innocent
it's deeper than
it's not it's not superficial politics
but it's deep politics
it's changing what could be even
possible in the realm of politics
okay that's great politics it's it's
it's kind of like
politics quote unquote is the space
where we hash out things according to
certain rules
the metapolitical is where we are
enabling ourselves to change the nature
of those rules that we call political
so like right now political action is
entirely strategic action
and you know sociopaths rise through the
ranks
as do you get in business and so the
question would be like if that's
politics then we need to change the
nature of politics but you can't do that
using politics as usual have to go
metapolitical which is why every time
there's a kind of civilizational
turnover there's a tremendous amount of
work
at the level of personhood education
logos that's why i think we're not in a
revolutionary time we're in a time of
renaissance of kind of
we need to rediscover our humanity on
some level
because we've been so damaged by the the
you know the state of things well that's
why i've been proposing the model of the
and i if you guys know my work i'm not
i'm not trying to i'm not not being
anachronistic
so i'm taking it as i'm not trying to
get back to it
but i'm proposing that we that we should
be thinking about something like the
axial revolution
rather than the french revolution as the
model we should be considering
uh because what happens in the axial
revolution
uh through the permeation
of all of the new psycho technologies is
entirely
that the cultural cognitive grammar has
changed so new ways of human being
and new ways of human religion and new
ways of human wisdom and new
ways of human spirituality become
possible for us
and um that's where i think we need to
go right now
because i think the issues we're facing
are
are are i think they're even more
profound than
what was going on i know what you're
trying to say andrew about the
renaissance but i think the issues we're
facing
are it's a much more significant
transition we might be going through
right now
even more than the renaissance a greater
a greater transition well i mean the
renaissance is wrestling with a lot of
things it's wrestling with
you know it's wrestling with uh the you
know the the
the the the corruption the decline of
the catholic church
it's wrestling with the rediscovery of
aristotelian science
neoplatonic
magic which by the way eventually gets
taken up
into advertising uh so that's a weird
uh history of its own so there's a lot
of things going on here
uh but i think i guess i'm more thinking
of the essence of the word renaissance
like rebirth rather than rather than the
specific
uh moment
i guess that's what i'm because i'm not
you know i'm not a historian
and but i think what
i guess what i want to what i want to
emphasize the difference is although
there was a lot of stuff
sort of maybe falling apart uh you know
on the cusp of the renaissance
i think we're under much more threat
of a much more comprehensive
kind of disaster and collapse
and so uh that's why i think of
you know the way people sort of come out
of the bronze age collapse
uh in the axial revolution it might be
more helpful
i don't know it's it's hard to know zach
is right this is
where we're in is very historically
unprecedented and so we have to take
these historical models
very carefully we shouldn't be really
attached to them really i've been
i've been trying to think of a few
because there's the the renaissance and
then that circuitous route through the
enlightenment and the 30 years war in
that period which was the
overthrow of the ancient regime and the
birth of capitalism nation state all
that stuff
and then there were hegemonic turnovers
within the history of capitalism right
from the
from the dutch uh well first from the
jawanese or the italians to the dutch
than the british than the united states
so there's one
so what is it like that lead up to world
war one
when it went from the british to the
united states and this capitalist
hegemony that's bigger than that
is it as big as the turnover of the
ancient regime into
the you know end of the feudal period
beginning the capitalist period
that one seems pretty resonant but now
you're saying well maybe it's like the
collapse of the bronze age
right at the beginning of the axial
revolution which is an even
deeper thing and then you could even ask
the question well is it actually as
significant as
uh when humans first began to use
language right now i was thinking about
that too
is it that deep or is it a significance
as the emergence of you know
multicellular organisms
from single cellular just saying like
what
kind of evolutionary transition are we
actually in
and the digital is pretty weird and
we've gone completely
planetary right and high technology
probably is even higher than we know
because of all the
you know dark money and you know
multiple ongoing manhattan projects have
been going on for the past 20 years so
like this
the chance that we're actually at a much
more profound
evolutionary mode
as opposed to like historical mode
sometimes is one of the things that
resonates with me
and then i go kind of religious
transhumanist and begin to reflect on
the radical radical possibilities of
personhood that may end up having to be
actualized
during this during this time because you
want to go into that a little bit
that's that's you we're talking a little
bit you were talking about that with
with jim rutt you were talking about
um you know well i mean it's what's the
expression you use transhuman um
religion i say religious transhumanism
just because transhumanism
you know much of the discussions like
kurzweil and and others
you know that there's actually an
eschatological
religious flavor to what they're talking
about anyway the nature of the
artificial intelligence overlords or
whatever they are
and then you know moving our
consciousness into silicon mainframes
and these kinds of things or even the
radical
kind of kind of bio hacking life
extension
to achieve physical immortality um
these you know getting beyond the human
ending but that's all sort of a
perversion isn't it i mean that's
this is what i'm saying i'm saying let's
put our religious cards actually on the
table
and if we're going to speculate about
you know
um futures for the species that actually
involve
the self-transformation of the species
into a new species
right christ was talking about that
right a lot of religious figures were
talking about in some way
that there's a there's a there's a
person hidden within our person that's
greater than any person
that we've ever known there's there's a
there's a there's a spiritual quantum
leap right a spiritual quantum leap
that's good i think about the television
show randomly but
but it is
like an acute evolutionary possibility
um and that you know tillyard and
norvinda would say things like you know
that the great religious
figures have been evolutionary outliers
messengers from the future as
it were showing what's possible at the
root of
the human personhood and so
yeah barbara mark's hustler barbara
marks hubbard and others
you know that merger of high technology
complete planetization
and radical existential risk it's a
pretty rich cocktail
for you know being being kind of you
know
it's a request from evolution for the
human to potentially
radically radically change um and in
that sense
then we're in a situation now that we we
don't actually understand what exactly
our situation is
that you can read it on historical
analogies but we're actually in the
middle of something
so big that we couldn't know like it's
it's it's uh and that doesn't mean we
can't act we actually can and there's a
whole thing to say about that how to act
even though
you don't have total clarity um
but in a sense i think there's a certain
recognition we have to have that yeah we
don't know and we actually can't we
can't now
okay so where how do we act from that
place of of unknowing
i mean i think it has to do with care i
think
like it has to do with moving back down
to where
actual certainty exists you know like my
love for my wife i'm pretty certain of
this
like you know whether or not we're in
some major evolutionary transformation
into uh you know i'm not certain of that
in any way
it's like but the certainty for the love
for my wife
right um in concrete situations
i can be certain about what the right
thing to do is in abstract conversation
it's hard to be certain
and there are definitely moral dilemmas
where it's not clear what the right
thing to do is
but there's plenty of cases where you
where
you know where you where there's a
there's a kind of a base
certainty at the level of the life world
that's given
um so long as we're in the space of
reason and not strategically acting then
it's muddy um so in a sense when you're
wandering in the wilderness
ontologically
in terms of the meta-narratives that
make sense for orienting
uh you can you can move you can come to
the local
to the you can return to the local which
isn't a turn to the particular
or the relative because the
is actually hidden uh in in these local
uh member i've used that phrase anthro
ontological common sense
right that there's a there's a deep
seeded
capacity to orient together around
things that are true and to treat one
another in certain ways in light of that
so those things i think we're still in
that realm of certainty
um you know disingenuous scientific
arguments that try to diffuse that
certainty with like arguments about
neurological determinism
uh and nihilistic materialism
trying to undercut what we know from
anthropological excuse me anthro
ontological common sense trying to
undercut that
but those are those are not good
arguments there's because science relies
on
on the ability to actually be in the
space of reason and not strategically
relate to one another if you're actually
doing science
so the snake eats at sail and we're
given the life world
in which we can care for one another um
and from that we can create tremendous
knowledge and do remarkable inquiry
um but uh i'm not gonna override that
in order to signal some allegiance to
some meta-narrative
you know i'm going to ground in that and
then explore meta-narrative from a basis
of of care this temple that i can bring
with me
everywhere a friend of mine is writing a
book
he calls it the wealth of neighborhoods
instead of the wealth of nations
um it's like and the idea is there's
there's so much in your neighborhood
like
just in your local neighborhood there's
so much for example garbage that could
be repurposed or
um i don't know about there's so much
there's so much you could do with your
intimate
near world um i don't know if i'm over
simplifying your
your your argument here but well i i
would like to
i think uh i have a slightly different
take on this i think it's ultimately
convergent but i thought
because i think i think we
are in a situation like where it's
plausible that we
yeah that we're facing something more
like an evolutionary change
because of complexity and because
of the emergence of ai these two things
and they're
synergistically operating together
they're going to put a demand
on us to change our conception of human
design uh what that fundamentally means
so my recommendation for this
and i don't think this is in competition
for what
zach is proposing but i propose
that we put a lot more emphasis
on our capacity of adaptivity
that we get a deeper understanding of
what that actually
is that's what a lot of my work around
relevance realization has been about
what is our capacity for adapting
uh and evolving get a deeper so
i mean this is this is to my mind a kind
of scientific take on the socratic
idea of self-knowledge which is not
autobiographical knowledge it's about
knowing
your capacities it's knowing the you
know
how you actually fundamentally operate
it's not your autobiography it's your
operation manual
and one of the interesting things we
could we have the potential to do
and it's part of what does happen um is
to take
the the advent of ai and the way
networks work in the internet and they
have all these deleterious
consequences we've been talking about
but they actually also afford us with
some powerful ways of understanding
our capacity for adapting and evolving
and potentially making that the
focus so so this is what i've been
trying to do with the reinvention of
notions like faith
and trust try to re-understand them in
terms
of ways in which we are accessing and
accentuating our capacity
uh for relevance realization and
adaptivity
because i think trying to come to a
conclusion
or as acts as trying to identify or
align with a meta-narrative
that is attempting some kind of closure
i think is massively presumptuous
precisely because
not only are we ignorant the rate at
which we are ignorant about
all of this is accelerated and i think
the i don't know dude if this is
convergent with what you're saying
zach it feels like it is because it
feels like we you know
we get a good understanding one of the
places where we get our best
understanding of how we
zero in on what's relevant how we adapt
and how we undergo
that constant evolution of our ability
to cognitively fit to the world
it is in our phenomenological
interaction i get that i think that's
one of the core moves
in foreign cognitive science but
i feel like we're not saying exactly the
same thing and we need to do something
to get them to
to be closer together uh i i see the
like i say this is
generally what i what i i guess in broad
strokes mean by
getting people to try and cultivate
wisdom is
how can we reliably
and with high plausibility and with new
tools
how can we use this to really enhance
people's
capacity to complexify in a way
that gives them an ongoing
fitted response to the ongoing
complexity of the world that's where i
think we should be
sort of devoting our resources uh in
this situation of ultimately not knowing
what the hell we are in
uh-huh so can i just try to say say that
both try to see if i can compress what
you two guys are saying in my own dumb
language um so so uh
what i hear zach saying is is a kind of
a return to the life
world in some kind of a way in the the
basic realities
of life and what i hear john saying is
is that we have to become more like
dancers we have to become more flexible
to to uncertainty and and um and so so i
feel there's a
movement towards perennialism and zach
and a movement towards futurism and
and john and and then maybe those are
the two things that have to come
together but
if i'm radically if i've got that
completely wrong please let me know
well i liked everything except the the
the that i i i
i i i wouldn't want futurism i would say
it's it's
maybe it's uh i don't know what it is
and it is in fact
it's just maybe it's the closest thing
to stoicism
is perhaps the the ism that would come
closest
the empire has come so complex uh you
try to enhance your capacity to
adapt uh so that you
can as reliably as possible act in a
virtuous manner
yeah and i i think the way they would
come together as i
i think i'm leading with
the space where those adaptations need
to take place like the materials and
complexities that get that adaptive
muscle going
are other people more so
or at least as much as uh you know the
objective world and complex
problems in the objective world of
adapting my physical body to it and
things of that nature and so i guess
and it may be implicit in what you're
saying but i'm saying that the
the place where that adaptive capacity
it's us
we are adapting not me adapting and you
adapting
we are adapting and so i think that's
what i'm saying is that it's
you know that yes return in a sense to
the
ability to always be learning and
growing
and like focusing on that and but in
fact that
is always involving other people and uh
something like that i think would be the
way to bring them together because i'm
agreeing it's not in a sense i'm not
saying return to some traditional
form of life it's actually the opposite
i'm i'm saying
return to one another so we can figure
out how to evolve together
um as as opposed to staying stuck as
isolated individuals
all independently of like kind of in
strategic evolutionary relationship i'm
saying that's a weird
model and fiction like that in fact
the the the reality is of deeply
embedded
relationality and that we are adapting
and then if i
if i adapt in a way that makes it so
that you can't adapt well
that sucks right so we need to we need
to code
i agree with that i think okay so i
think that's what comes together i think
because i think our most significant i
mean
i think this is it shouldn't be in any
way questionable
our most significant additivity is
exactly our ability to
um engage sophisticated distributed
cognition that's our that's our main
way of adapting to the world i mean uh
our biggest advantage is culture
that we generate culture which is a way
in which
we basically network brains together to
make something
way more synergistically powerful than
they're individually capable on their
own
so i if that's what you're talking about
and that's again why
i think it's so important to try and
replace the monological
model of reason with the dialogical
model of reasoning
that we reason best in distributed
cognition and that's again where the
cognitive science is pointing it's
pointing
out that we reason much better in groups
than we ever do individually and i've
tried to make that i've tried to make
that a phenomenologically salient thing
for people
that when you get into genuine via logos
with people
both people can come to places that they
couldn't get to on their own
and that has an aesthetic to it there's
something beautiful there's something
lovely in the sense of lovable about
that and
and it's tremendously motivating for
people and this is what i mean about
trying to steal the culture if we can
get people oriented towards these things
so they experience reliably the
motivation to want to enter into that
we we could do something like what the
christians did to the roman empire
we can build a a alternative culture
underneath
this horribly oppressive regime that
eventually can actually
you know undermine its undermine it
without
you know what you might call a political
revolution or
or you know burning things in the street
that's what i
that's what i'm really really interested
because where where
there have been those moves where people
you know that's what i mean by that
slogan i have actually there's come out
right now with here the dawn that
has done the meaning wave will steal the
culture that's what i mean by steal the
culture
if we can if we can get people into
directly tasting and
savoring what it's like to experience
that overflow of rationality
and i mean that term very broadly that
is possible
in distributed cognition the way it it
enhances our additivity
but like with the same kind of
motivational presence as the flow state
does for individuals
i think that is a way of you know
weaning
people off the addiction to the toxic
aspects of social media and you talked
about beauty too which seems to be a
very important part of it right
being able to reconnect to beauty right
and that's we're coming back to our last
discussion with
um and you so so that that is the
ugliness
is in the transactional relationship
right
very much very much i mean there's a
sense in which
what like if we can get people to see
i i'm struggling for that it's apprehend
it's it's participated the
the the fact that there is a way of
being like socratic dialogue is not just
a presentation of arguments
it is it is it is the seduction to a way
of life
it is offering a direct experience of a
way of being
that's an enactive symbol for how we can
be
fundamentally aroused
differently care differently than we do
now that can
wean us off an addiction to
you know that's what plato's project was
an addiction to
right really disastrous social political
organizations
i mean that's why he he saw what was
happening to athens and he wanted to
create an alternative
beautiful i mean i completely agree and
uh
this is why we get along because it's
such a richly educative
vision i mean it's really about putting
true
sincere inquiry
collective inquiry and engagement
account at the heart near the heart of
culture like right
and yeah that is and then what you end
up doing is you you kind of
if you want to use kind of gerardian
terms you kind of flip
the direction of memetic desire and turn
it towards the good
so that now what becomes sexy and what
people want to do
what gets their endorphins going and
makes them excited ends up being
something that is
that actually is not beneficial to their
participation in it
and it's much more in their control
that's the other thing you remember is
that you actually
you know all of the mechanisms by which
communication happens on social media
are
captured and commodified but
conversation
is it's different and to to remove it
from the realm of commodification and
return it
to the completely non-strategic to the
real
uh the real yeah and that's and i think
there's
you know i think there is um there's a
potency to it
you know like there and there's a need
for it actually as well
when you think about the kind of
hierarchies of needs models you know
that need for self-transcendence
and for self-actualization can only be
achieved in those kinds of
interpersonal context dialogical context
you can't really actually see achieve
self-transcendence
and self-actualization in digitally
mediated asynchronous
text-based interactions you just it's
just not going to happen you can signal
that you're
that you're post-conventional or
whatever but to actually be so richly
steeped
in these types of exchanges that
you see the fluidity of your own
identity with those of others and
and the possibilities you said the
overflow of reason i really like that
because that's there's an excess
of reasonability and goodness
right there um and
yeah that's what you find in those
precious contexts
of the life world like the mother child
relationship
right or the legitimate teacherly
authority
student-teacher relationship like there
are there are places where it just
becomes
so clear that this is a species-specific
trait
like this this way of interacting
and using language and uh
the memetic um seduction to a
a different way of life as you're saying
like so you mean like a positive kind of
imitation so you you imitate your
your you're if you're a child you
imitate your mother if you're a student
you
you imitate the teacher but not copy him
you just
yeah you get this transmission from him
which
raises the level of your own um
perceptions and
it's a basic psychological construct
gerard got it from
the french psychologist tarde who also
influenced
james mark baldwin who influenced psja
and
you know baldwin's whole model entire
days was based on the imitations the
basic driver of
personality and cognitive development
and
gerard yeah yeah gerard kind of plugged
right into that
and then noted just that violence is one
of those things that is particularly
imitatable
and prone to be like um attractive for
imitation so
so the notion of memetic violence and
mimetic desire
um came out of a psychological lineage
of thinking about imitation as a basic
mechanism
but you don't have to attach invitation
to violence
like we imitate across the board across
a whole range of things
and uh so yeah but is there is there a
space beyond imitation or is it just
always that right
quote andrew you know where zach says
flipping
uh you know gerard's notion of flipping
the direction the moment of desire
that's the virtuous officer
steferson is basically at the education
of your salience landscaping so you're
tempted to the good
that's what it means yeah that's what
that's why it's in contrast to incratia
right yeah i like that you're naturally
tempted towards the good and and
so so it's making desire it's making
desire a positive
and passion and and uh you know all the
emotions a positive force rather than a
rather than uh something that has turned
against you and that you enacting
unconsciously
to destroy yourself and others right
that's one of the things socrates
claimed to know
he claimed to know erotica which is what
means he
he had he had he had its officement in
the sense he knew what to care about and
how to care about it well
that's education again ah that's really
amazing actually
i mean that seems to be the purpose of
education knowing what to care about and
how to care about it well i mean
would you agree with that zach or i mean
it should be yeah
that's what you say you said you said
you say your primary concern is
care um and and also your primary
concern is education
and it just occurred to me that
you know that that's what education is
about
on the most fundamental level or should
be about right it should be
and and it comes down to something that
was said earlier about
you know you have to be trying to solve
the right problem
or it's not worth solving and so so much
of education they give you the problem
and you're just supposed to solve it um
but
the figuring out how to know what
problem is a good problem to even be
working on yeah right
formulation right then and the
cultivation
and clarification of desires another way
to say that and so
you know if if education gives you what
you want that's like advertising right
again
that's that's uh design it's not you get
a degree or something
yeah yeah so it's about the raising of
someone isn't
giving them telling them or forcing them
to solve a problem they may or may not
want to solve
it's getting in them equipped to think
about the kind of life that they
want to pursue right to frame the
problem of their
of their own development and uh yes i
really like this idea of
you know tipping the balance within
oneself so that you're seduced towards
the good
and that's what it is and you're seduced
towards let's say growth as well
yeah and i can't tell you growing up
like a
continual growth process uh rather than
you know you arrive somewhere right it's
not like enlightenment it's just
continual growth
it may be it may be in many areas just
continuous growth
you know and and there's an important
difference in terms of like values
education you know it's not
our place to actually tell you what's
good for you it's to equip you to figure
out what's good for you
um and this is this is so much of what
some of the justice conversation hinges
around you know it hinges around
the way we are able to uh
care for one another uh in ways that
don't slide into uh paternalism
right and design um
and and that's so that's it's a critical
educational issue and it's one of the
one of the reasons that we've so
problematized teacher early authority in
general
is that we haven't disentangled it from
paternalism and so much education is
paternalistic
you know like so we just throw out the
role models uh completely right
you threat i talk to my students and i
say like do you have any heroes or
is there anybody you look up to or that
you you know you aspire to be like and
some of them say no
you know it's like they don't want to
have they don't want to have role models
they don't want to have muddles they
just want to be themselves
but that's that's a dead end that's a
we need this mimetic process of
imitating and the world
who are greater than and and and
wiser than and and more you know than we
are
who we can imitate yeah who we can
imitate right exactly
and uh yeah that's part of that
disruption of
intergenerational transmission is that
diffusing of the potency of potential
role models just across the board
and uh the retreat to the
self and the screen as the locus
of ideal the formation of ideals and
um you know because if you're starting
to aspire to
if you're getting your messages of what
you're supposed to imitate not from your
screen
[Music]
then they've lost and you've won so
they're going to try to diffuse all the
possibilities of you
finding a way to shape your identity
outside of that
um that context of strategic
design so yeah so there's a dire need i
completely agree with john to you know
to return to these spaces of dialogue
and to rekindle actual teacherly
authority you know to rekindle these
contexts of
real socialization and uh you know
deep reciprocal identity shaping
um yep that would be that's
it i would say it's even you're saying
it's maybe it's deeper than the
political
it's way deeper i mean this is an
existential risk thing like if we can't
figure out how to do this
then pretty much everything's lost
because eventually it'll just
the inability to have real sincere
earnest collective inquiry will
go all the way up into all echelons of
institutions and then the
you know that one outcome is war
right another war of all against all or
whatever and another outcome is just
uh the degradation of actual physical
and technical infrastructures because
remember science
runs on these this kind of process it
has to if
if scientists start lying to one another
and everyone thinks everyone's lying to
everybody then science is actually not
getting done
uh if science is everyone's strategic
against everyone else and vying for
funds and
yeah then it's not it's not actually
science science requires
uh actual earnest collective
inquiry um and so when that's when it
starts to break down the realm of
science that's like oh
is that nuclear reactor actually going
to work or not
like will the electrical grid actually
stay up or won't it uh as things get
more complicated we actually need to
preserve the space of reason to actually
solve the problems to keep our
basic systems running um and
uh so yeah it's a it's a very serious
issue it's top top of the list and one
of the hardest to work on
precisely because it seems uh not as
complicated and technical as some fancy
scientific problem it's just about
finding ways to get people together um
and so yeah the the question of how to
propagate out through the field
these kinds of practices that you're
recommending john i think is
is essential um how to create pockets
and culture where that
emerges as an attractor right where that
becomes something to imitate
is is very important
and then it doesn't become it doesn't
lose its power or something if things
get too big
you know if something becomes a movement
sometimes it loses its power so there
seems to be
a size there seems to be a a size of of
how that can work like
there has to be an intimate relationship
but between each person
in in the problem that's trying to be be
solved
otherwise it becomes abstract am i
making sense here or
am i well i think you are but i don't
think it's just a size issue
because you know we've got evidence
about metastable systems
systems can be stable at different
orders of complexity
um i think it's more important to look
at certain features
you know what's coming to mind right now
is dewey's argument
about the way democracy is a
self-correcting process and science is a
self-correcting process
and therefore they need each other
dramatically uh
but but what dewey didn't really
understand enough or
maybe he did i don't want to be unfair
to him but one one way
you can turn this into a
an issue to reflect on is well
what dewey is presupposing is people's
ability to commit to
and value a process of self-correction
for its own sake
uh because when you have right when you
have systems like democracy
and science in which the process within
distributed cognition
of self-correction is considered what is
valued most
rather than any particular product or
result and the systems can actually
especially if you have two of those
coordinated together then then the
structure can actually become
quite large and complex without
sort of generating um into the kind of
thing you're worrying about
andrew the systems aren't capable of
metastability right but they know that
the
thing could be scaled like the catholic
church a billion people
or um i don't know
sorry to just use a more
what were you going to say zach i was
going to say you like you're correct but
you have to like
almost at the level of the fractal
infuse the
thing with the with the proper
weightings of what is valued as you're
saying so like exactly
exactly it's a very very kind of complex
actually
cognitive value to value process over
product right which is what you're
saying that like the
people very very people within democracy
need to value democratic process
more than they value some particular
outcome exactly
same as science right people within
science need to value
the scientific exactly exactly i reckon
and so that's dewey's underlying insight
is that
and he he took it up from charles
sanders purse who was
about the ethics of inquiry that in fact
science depends upon things like honesty
cooperation and selflessness because if
you're really part of science
then you know sign when you're dead
science will change and you're
contributing to something that's larger
than even your lifetime and you're kind
of
making a self-transcendent move to put
your life on the altar of
science basically this person's idea and
so
so yeah there's uh yeah julie's due's
point is deep but
you know it is also as you're saying
demanding and he's not yes
with a demand habermas who was was
massively influenced by dewey as a youth
actually
uh you know just after world war ii some
of the only reading materials in germany
were like these
john dewey books that the that the
united states military brought in
to indoctrinate the germans and it
really worked
and his political theory between facts
and values
between facts and norms rather uh he
makes the same move
you know both self-regulating
auto-correcting systems science and
democratic process
in the space of reasons but he doesn't
specify just how demanding it is
cognitively to participate in those
and in terms of in terms of the
commitment and so there's a kind of what
i've called the cognitive maturity
fallacy
which ends up plaguing a lot of
philosophy which is the assumption that
uh high-level cognitive capacities are
are given when they're not they're
actually an educational achievement
which may or may not be exactly right
so um i think dewey's modeling of
democracy and hormones
basically assumes a very well
functioning educational system
um and you know do we saw that equation
and how vermont sees that equation
but i think uh yeah you know
some of what you're describing it's it's
the condition for the body the dialogos
condition for the possibility of both
science and
democracy yeah so uh
zach you you you put a term to the thing
i was sort of trying to articulate about
the
yeah what was being presupposed what
what was the what did you the cognitive
maturity fallacy
the cognitive maturity fallacy yeah yeah
that's good
i like that that's very tasty that could
be like iq or something
and you find it all throughout
epistemology like when you read
especially analytical philosophy
things like that they're they're talking
about like you know the mind as if
they've never met a little kid
yeah yeah yeah yeah whereas psja is like
whoa that fall formal logic thing
doesn't kick in until really late
if ever by the way that people can do
hypothetical deductive reasoning for
real
uh so there's this yeah as a
developmentalist
i was basically saying uh the most
interesting this is a paper that i wrote
which will be out
soon i was basically saying the most and
one of the most interesting things about
psja
uh and cam wilbur to some extent is that
they don't commit the cognitive
maturities
fallacy that they actually model
epistemology at multiple levels
um and uh and then the other factor of
the cognitive maturity fallacy is that
uh that you have achieved maturity yeah
yeah
you assume mature the others that
there's not levels beyond your
epistemology
is also part of the cognitive maturity
policy so it's an interesting concept
but you
you've seen in political theorizing and
in other places as well where there's
just an assumption that the baseline
of human capacity is actually far more
sophisticated
and that what they're doing there what
they should actually do is
well maybe every everything's a nail
when i've got this hammer but what they
should actually do is
characterize the issue as in part also
an educational issue yeah
i agree i agree that in fact you know
thinking about structures of science and
law and governance also requires
thinking about the educational systems
that produce scientists and lawyers and
and politicians and if you place the bar
pretty high uh
in you know no pun intended with the
legal thing if you place the bar really
high
and the education systems don't get
people there then you're
you've failed to reproduce the you know
the the society
and that's one of the situations we're
in so yeah so there's a
kind of a massive need for psycho
emotional cognitive triage to be run
across the whole bunch of
areas the thing and the things you're
rolling out john seemed to be
some of the best of going you know
i should get going gentlemen uh but
as always this has been wonderful
i really enjoyed uh zach some of the
extended
um i don't know what to call them
they're not speeches because that's the
wrong way but
the extended presentations you made
because i got to see some of the depth
of your thinking
and to really appreciate it so i wanted
to thank you for that
that was really quite wonderful at times
thank you john
likewise there's an opportunity here
when we speak
again to say things i wouldn't i was
like
and i think probably the same for you
you end up saying things you wouldn't
say
if you were speaking to somebody else so
there's a no there's a really unique
relationship
that's the that's the marker of dia
logos that's really the market of it
and i i'm honored to be sandwiched in
between you two guys
and uh uh i feel like uh i feel like
there was one point where i i just i
lost the thread
but it was but it was but i was i was
almost i almost had the thread and then
right towards the end i was
i was i was i was losing the thread a
little bit because you're going into
realms which i don't particularly
understand but uh
um i'm sorry but no no no problem at all
that's not a complaint that's just like
you guys are blowing blowing my
my mind as always and that was great
as as always all right gentlemen i'm
happy to do this again
uh every time i've done this i've found
it fruitful and
zach you seem to find it also so
whenever you want to do this again
consider me it totally
i'll get a haircut next time i'll be
looking less like the unabomber
[Laughter]
no that's perfect i guess
i really gotta jump guys take care good
night see ya thanks thanks so much
bye-bye